A Guide to the A. Patrick L. Prest, Jr. papers, 1941-2014
Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
A. Patrick L. Prest, Jr. papers
1941-2014
Tompkins-McCaw Library
Prest, A. Patrick L., Rev., Jr.
2016.11.69
5.1 Linear Feet 10 doc cases, 1 print box
Access Restrictions
The collection is open to research; however, some files with confidential information are restricted.
Acquisition Information
The papers were donated by the Department of Patient Counseling in the School of Allied Health Professionals at Virginia Commonwealth University in November 2016.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Rev. Dr. Alan Patrick Llewelyn Prest, Jr. was born in Detroit, Michigan and grew up in Massachusetts. He earned a degree in business from Lehigh University in 1951 before receiving his Masters of Divinity from the Episcopal Theological Seminary in Cambridge, Massachusetts in 1954. Following his residency in clinical pastoral education at St. Luke's Hospital in Houston, Texas, Prest served a chaplain at Bellevue Hospital in New York City.
After a short tenure at Bellevue, Prest came to the Medical College of Virginia (MCV) where he succeeded the Rev. Dr. George D. Ossman who had served as the first chaplain and as a clinical pastoral educator beginning in 1943. The MCV administration tasked Prest with securing accreditation for the clinical pastoral education program which had been initiated in 1958. Under Prest's leadership the program received accreditation from the Council for Clinical Training (now the Association for Clinical Pastoral Education) one year later. During the pastoral education program's formative years, Prest served as administrator and hospital chaplain. He also established a cooperative program with the School of Theology at Virginia Union University (VUU) for which he was an adjunct instructor teaching courses in pastoral counseling and clinical orientation.
The educational program with Prest at the helm remained administratively part of the MCV Hospital until the creation of Virginia Commonwealth University in 1968. The VCU Board of Visitors established a new school for the allied health programs at the former MCV and the program in pastoral counseling was a logical choice for this new administrative home. This move split the education program from the pastoral care service component and the latter remained based in the hospital as the department of pastoral care. Prest remained responsible for both units and coordinated both units as they trained counselors and provided pastoral care in the hospital. The Board of Visitors promoted Prest to full professor and acknowledged his administrative role by naming him chair of the Program in Patient Counseling. He continued in this role until his retirement in 1993.
In addition to his work at VCU, Prest devoted time to professional activities. In 1967 he organized the Virginia Institute for Pastoral Care, one of the oldest pastoral counseling centers in the United States. The Institute supported both the MCV and University of Virginia chaplaincy programs as they struggled to secure adequate funding to sustain their respective programs. Prest also helped to organize the Virginia Association for Allied Health Professionals and served as its first president. He was also active with the Virginia Board of Professional Counselors for a period of eleven years, including two terms as chair.
Following Prest's retirement, the program in patient counseling continued to develop and it finally received departmental status within the School of Allied Health Professions in 2010. The Master of Science degree program was established in 2000 and a dual-degree arrangement with the School of Theology at VUU began. In 2007 the department enrolled its first students in pastoral counseling track of the School of Allied Health Professions' doctoral program in health related sciences. The department also initiated a distance learning program at New College in Abingdon and Memorial Hospital in Martinsburg, Virginia. Thanks to the generosity of the Lantz family the department established two endowed positions, the Rev. Robert B. Lantz Chair of the Department of Patient Counseling and the Katherine I. Lantz Professor of Patient Counseling.
Sources:
"A Brief History of CPE at MCV" (see box:folder 3:12)
VCU School of Allied Health Professions, Patient Counseling, History of Personnel (http://sahp.vcu.edu/departments/ptc/about-us/history-of-personnel/)
VCU School of Allied Health Professions, Patient Counseling, Program History (http://sahp.vcu.edu/departments/ptc/about-us/program-history/)
Scope and Contents
The Prest papers are comprised mostly of materials pertaining to his work as a hospital chaplain and educator. There are some materials contained in the collection from the Department of Patient Counseling that date after Prest's retirement in 1993. These papers offer insight into how the Clinical Pastoral Education (CPE) program was formed and administered as well as trends in the professionalization of clinical pastoral care. The collection is divided into six series. Materials of particular interest are detailed in the series descriptions.
Series 1 MCV/VCU, 1954-2014. This series includes papers, publications, reports, accreditation materials, correspondence, and memoranda related to the pastoral care program at the Medical College of Virginia (MCV) and later Virginia Commonwealth University (VCU).
The accreditation materials for the Council for Clinical Training and the Association for Clinical Pastoral Education provide information on the early days of the program and includes examples of program activities, self-studies, and site reports required for the accreditation process. Since these materials span from 1957 to 2010 it also illustrates how the accreditation process has evolved.
Various reports in this series offer insight into how the program functioned as well as how it expanded and changed over time. The annual reports of the Chaplains' Department supply a summary of activities and statistics from the first decade of the program. A 1964 Old Dominion Foundation grant application demonstrates how the program was growinig and in need of funds to support its expanding mission and the 1975 mission and goals report and the 1987 Virginia Cluster report highlight trends and changes in pastoral education.
Additional materials of interest are a group of letters between 1968 and 1970 discussing whether the CPE program violated Article IV Section 67 of the Virginia Constitution regarding the separation of church and state. Also of interest are the chapel bulletins from the 1950s-1970s used for the four services held on Sundays at the hospital. In addition to detailing the order of service, the bulletins contain announcements about patient counseling services and a devotional or meditation usually written by one of the counselor-chaplains.
Other materials in the series include the hospital chaplain's log books summerizing interactions with patients and their families, hosptial chapel information, proposals for a master's degree in patient counseling, articles, clippings, and newsletters featuring the department and staff, photographs, and a scrapbook.
Series 2: Council for Clinical Training (CCT), 1953-1977. The series consists of materials such as correspondences, newsletters, reports, and conference programs and papers. The documents in this series provide some insight into the organization responsible for accrediting the CPE program and personnel at MCV when it was established. There is one folder of materials for the Association for Clinical Pastoral Education (ACPE) which is the current accrediting body. CCT merged with three other organizations in 1967 to form ACPE. Of interest in this series are the evaluations of Prest during his tenure at St. Luke's which were submitted to CCT for his accreditation with the organization.
Series 3: Writings, 1967-1986. This series is comprised of articles and manuscripts drafts written by Prest and others as well as presentation notes and text. Subjects explored include suicide, death and dying, and grief.
Series 4: Subject Files, 1941, 1955-1984. The series contains articles and materials concerning topics of interest to Prest.
Series 5: Educational Papers, 1952-1954. In this series are papers from his time as a student at Episcopal Theological Seminary and includes class assignments, lecture notes, and exams.
Series 6: Virginia Union University, 1968-1989. This series contains materials relating to his work as an adjunct professor including syllabi, course assignments, and some faculty materials such as meetings and minutes.
Prest, A. Patrick L., Rev., Jr.; Virginia Commonwealth University. School of Allied Health Professions. Department of Patient Counseling
- Series 1: MCV/VCU, 1954-2014
  - Christmas, Chapel Bulletin, 1957-1967, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Easter, Chapel Bulletins, 1958-1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Thanksgiving, Chapel Bulletins, 1957-1967, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sunday Chapel Bulletins, 1962-1976 (Box 1, Folder 4-8)
  - Chaplain's log books (ACCESS RESTRICTED), 1968-1978 (Box 2, Folder 1-10)
  - Accreditation materials, CCT (ACCESS RESTRICTED), 1957, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Summaries of Prest's group sessions with students where they discussed interactions with patients and case studies. These include Prest's evaluation of students during the session.
  - Accreditation materials, CCT, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Includes the schedule and lectures from "A Series of Eight Lectures of Concern to Theologican and Physicians" sponsored by the Chaplain's Department and a copy of the orientation program schedule for CPE students.
  - Accreditation materials, ACPE, 1974, 1986, 2000, 2005, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 3-7)
  - ACPE Mid-Atlantic Region timeline, 1954-2014 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Annual reports, 1960, 1964, 1967, 1968, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Committal service for donor bodies, undated, 1986, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - General correspondence, 1958-1998 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Prest correspondence, 1954-1982 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Good Gried Conference registration programs, 1995, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Historical background file about Department of Patient Counseling and Pastoral Care, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Hospital Chapel dedication, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Hospital Chapel materials, 1967, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Includes information on symbols of different religions, 1967 design floor plans, letter about possible renovation, 1992.
  - Robert B. Lantz Chair in Patient Counseling, 2006-2011 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Loftis Scholarship, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Mission and goals report for Patient Counseling, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Old Dominion Foundation grant application, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - George Ossman articles, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Patient Counseling site visit report, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Pat Prest CV and certificate of appreciation, 1990, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Professional Consultation Committee and Patient Counseling Advisory Committee, 1994-1999 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Includes agendas, minutes, and notes, for some of the meetings of the committees.
  - Proposal for MS degree, Patient Counseling, 1974, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Proposal to SCHEV for MS degree, Patient Counseling, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Richmond Veterans Administration Hospital and Patient Counseling Training Program, memoramdum of understanding, undated, 1986, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Self-Study Committee minutes, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Sentara Hospital Student Handbook (administrative section), 2002-2003 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Statistical report for Dept. of Patient Counseling, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Student evaluations of Pat Prest, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Student tuition, stipend memos, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Tartaglia Scholarship and Prest Lecture, 2012-2014 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Virginia Cluster for Pastoral Education Response to Site Team Recommendations, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Articles, newsletters, and pamphlets, 1958-2013 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1958-1990 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Photographs, undated, 1958, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Scrapbook, 2013 (Box 11)
    A Ride Down Memory Lane, Highways to Healing, created as part of the celebration of 55 years of clinical pastoral education and 70 years of pastoral care at VCU. Includes photographs and bios of staff as well as copies of articles and documents related to the VCU Department of Patient Counseling and the Department of Pastoral Care at VCU Medical Center.
- Series 2: Council for Clinical Training (CCT), 1953-1977
  - Accreditation documents, St. Luke's Hospital, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    The documents pertain to Prest's work as an assistant supervisor at St. Luke's Hospital in Houston, Texas. The materials include self-evaluations by Prest and reports from his training supervisor, Armen D. Jorjorian.
  - Annual Conference of Supervisors, St. Louis, Missouri, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Includes the conference schedule, papers from presenters, workshop information, committee reports, and membership list.
  - Applications for clinical pastoral training, 1956-1957 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Council materials, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Includes form letters, newsletters, committee reports, budget information, and similar materials related to the organization.
  - General papers, 1953-1959 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Includes miscellaneous pamphlets, correspondence, and articles related to CCT or pastoral education in general.
  - National Conference on Clinical Pastoral Education, 1957-1960 (Box 5, Folder 6-9)
    Includes conference programs, papers, committee reports, and notes from the 1957 and 1958 national conferences; minutes of the Regional Conference for Institutional Chaplains in 1958 as well as some related correspondence; and correspondence about the southeastern region of the NCCPE meeting in Richmond, Virginia in 1960 and includes the handout titled "Discussion Questions in Clinical Pastoral Education.
  - Association for Clinical Pastoral Education, correspondence and reports, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Series 3: Writings, 1967-1986
  - "Critical Learning and Critical Analysis," Prest and Griffin, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - "Death and Dying" manuscript, 1967-1969 (Box 6, Folder 3-2)
  - Lectures, articles, and presentations, undated, 1976, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Llewellyn manuscript, "A Hard Look at Suicide", 1982 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - "Reasonable Suicide," correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - "Thanaprayer - Prayer for Death", 1979 (Box 6, Folder 7-8)
- Series 4: Subject Files, 1941, 1955-1984
  - Articles of interest, undated, 1960-1979 (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
  - Chaplain's department articles and photographs, undated, 1958, 1976, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Church and state, undated, 1967-1982 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Euthanasia, 1971-1975 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - George Polk lecture, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Lamentations and grief, 1977-1978 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Monumental Church, 1941, 1978-1979 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Prest administration lecture notes, 1982-1984 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - A.P.L. Prest, Sr. Memorial Lectureship, 1974-1981 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Rational Suicide, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Revised Episcopal hymnal, 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 13-14)
  - Revised Episcopal hymnal, 1981-1982 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Special services (programs and notes), 1955-1960 (Box 8, Folder 2-3)
  - Society for Health and Human Values, 1971-1977 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Series 5: Educational Papers, 1952-1954
  - Exams and seminary papers, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 5-6)
  - Exams and seminary papers, 1952-1953 (Box 8,9, Folder 7,1)
  - Exams and seminary papers, 1952-1953 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Series 6: Virginia Union University, 1968-1989
  - Course planning and scheduling, 1984-1988 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Pastoral care course, PT 730, Pastoral Counseling, 1968-1989 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Pastoral care course, PT 731, Clinical Orientation, 1980-1988 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Pastoral care essays, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Faculty agendas and minutes of meetings, 1984-1988 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - General correspondence, undated, 1982-1989 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Photographs (faculty, staff, students), undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - School of Theology tour, agenda and prayer, 3-Jan-89 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Contracts (ACCESS RESTRICTED), 1981-1988 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Student course evaluations (ACCESS RESTRICTED), 1970s-1980s (Box 10, Folder 2-5)
  - Verbatims (ACCESS RESTRICTED), 1987 (Box 10, Folder 6)